hey there it's jamie and welcome back to
my channel i hope you find this video
helpful it's basically going to go over
my whole process of how i
embroider i'm going to talk about the
tools that i use optional items that
just make embroidery easier beginner
stitches slash my favorite stitches i
purposely made a pattern that is a
beginner embroidery pattern where each
stem and flower uses a different stitch
that i am showing you how to use that's
going to be linked down below in my etsy
shop if you want to embroider along with
that one no pressure though you can
totally just use your hoop if you want
to practice these stitches i do highly
recommend practicing the stitches seeing
how many embroidery stitches there are
out there can be a little bit
intimidating so just trying them out and
finding your favorites makes patterns a
lot less intimidating and especially if
you're going into make your own patterns
then you know which stitches that you
like to use in order to create the look
that you're going for so again if you
want to use my pattern that's going to
be linked in my etsy shop below but yeah
i'm just going to take you through my
whole process step by step this is
definitely a beginner tutorial if you
already know the basics this video is
going to be very redundant for you but
feel free to watch if you'd like you
might learn something new and towards
the end of this video i just have a time
lapse of me finishing the project but i
made sure to have the voiceover of that
last section be a little q a because i
do receive a decent amount of the same
questions in the comment section on my
embroidery videos so i thought i might
as well answer those questions in this
one here there's a lot to go over so
without further ado let's get into the
video
so starting off with the essential tools
i use these wooden embroidery hoops for
my finished projects they come in all
sizes i typically use the five inch
but i highly recommend you get these
plastic embroidery hoops while you're
working on the project
they have a little nook on the inside
that catches the fabric and keeps it
from slipping while you're working on it
and if my project is for a five inch
embroidery hoop then i'll use one size
up for the plastic so i have a little
bit of wiggle room
emc embroidery floss is my favorite
thread and they also have these little
thread holders that you can wind your
thread onto so it prevents it from
getting tangled
hand sewing needles any ones will do
really
scissors i have fabric scissors as well
as pinking shears those give a zigzag
edge to your project so that the fabric
doesn't fray
and then i also recommend getting tiny
little baby scissors to cut the tail
ends of your embroidery thread
i embroider on cotton fabric i like it
much better than cross stitch fabric
because this allows you to freely
embroider wherever you want you can see
it is pretty thin here that's what i
like
if you want a more rustic look a canvas
fabric is also a great option
some kind of pattern is always helpful i
usually print mine out and then i trace
it onto the fabric i like using this led
light pad for my tracing totally
optional though if you watch my how i
design embroidery patterns then you'll
see me using a window in that one
instead of this light pad
for tracing i always use a mechanical
pencil and to finish my projects i use
hot glue to explain the stitches i'm
going to be using 1 2 3 to explain where
the stitches are going into the fabric
and coming out of it for the back stitch
we're coming up at one
going down for two
and then we'll come up for number three
and that will go back down into the
first number one
[Music]
and then we'll come up for four
and go back down into three
and so on and so forth
and a tip for the back stitch is if you
want to do curves using it then make
your stitches shorter distances apart
[Music]
moving on to the split stitch we come up
at one
go down for two
and then you'll come up for three
and your fourth stitch is going to be in
between one and two
[Music]
and now that next stitch will go down
back in between three and four i'm only
using two strands of embroidery floss so
this stitch definitely works better when
you have more strands and typically you
want the stitches to be closer together
than what i'm doing here to really get
that braided effect but i spread them
out so that you could see it better on
camera
the stem stitch you are coming up at one
going down at two this time in front of
your stitch
and you're not going to pull it all the
way through you're gonna come up at
three in between one and two and come
out over through the side
so this becomes your starter stitch now
you're gonna go down don't pull all the
way through
and go up
in between those two stitches
and pull off to the side
this is another stitch that works best
when the stitches are closer together
and it's great for curves
the lazy daisy stitch you are coming up
for one and you're going back down
either through that one or
right next to it so that'll be the
second one and then don't pull it all
the way through you're gonna hold on to
that loop
and then you'll come up for three
just wherever and however big you want
the petal to be
then you're gonna just pull that through
the loop you've made and then pull it
tight there's your little petal and
going down for four on the other side of
that loop to secure it
my tip for this one is to make sure not
to pull the petals too tight or else
they close up and it doesn't really look
like a petal anymore you can see i
accidentally did that because i grabbed
the knot behind the fabric
next up is going to be my favorite
stitch which is satin stitch right now
i'm showing you how to make a leaf using
it but this is also debatably a lazy
fishbone stitch you come up for one
down for two
and then three will be
next two and slightly lowered than your
first stitch
and then you'll go back down into two
and then for four you're gonna do next
two and slightly lowered on the opposite
side go back down into two and you're
gonna repeat that process just going out
and slightly lowered back down into two
and then this creates a little leaf
[Music]
using it as more of a fill-in stitch now
come up at one
down at two
and then at the same height as one
you're gonna come next to it for three
back down into two this is how i make my
other leaves in this project and how i
use the petals
but the satin stitch becomes a fill-in
stitch if instead of constantly going
back down into two
you just go back down next to the bottom
stitch like i am doing for the top here
and you can see i'm gradually getting
lower and i'm rounding my top more but
you can do that technique for both sides
and you'll have more of a circle in the
end rather than this teardrop shape
[Music]
the french knot stitch we're coming up
at one
and then using two hands for this one
we're holding our thread tight
looping it around our needle twice and
coming back down for two
right next to that number one stitch
hold it tight and pull it all the way
through and that's how you make a little
knot
showing it again we come up for one
loop it around the needle twice
and go back down for two
[Music]
last stitch i'm showing off is the
fishbone stitch come up for one
down for two
and then this is obviously easier if you
have a leaf drawn on but we're coming up
for three slightly lowered and next to
our first stitch and then you're making
a diagonal where the leaf is going to be
the widest width and that's for four
coming up for five on the opposite side
slightly lowered
and then go directly across
to the widest width of the leaf
and go down
and then we're just repeating that
pattern
of going next to and slightly lowered
diagonally and then going slightly under
our previous diagonal
and we are crisscrossing this doing
every other side
[Music]
so these are the beginner stitches that
i like to use the most and i use in most
of my projects
and now i'll walk you through step by
step how i make my project so grab your
embroidery hoop like i mentioned i use
the plastic ones with the little grip
cut out a square of fabric bigger than
the hoop you're using and i am using a
five inch embroidery pattern so i am
embroidering onto a slightly bigger
plastic hoop
lay your fabric over your hoop you can
iron it i never do though because i just
pull it really tight to get rid of those
wrinkles i just repeat the process of
tightening it and pulling the fabric
until it is tight and sounds a little
bit like a drum when you tap it now i
use my light pad to trace on my patterns
but you can use a window or you can also
put a light under a
glass coffee table if you want to
replicate this effect
and i'm showing you here that i
embroider on technically the back side
of the embroidery hoop with these
plastic ones so i can lay my fabric
completely flat onto my drawing
and then i can trace directly onto it
[Music]
once you're done tracing i usually touch
up my drawing just a little bit
and then i grab my embroidery thread
now in case you don't know embroidery
floss is made of six different strands
so whenever a project says to use one
strand or two strands or maybe it'll say
strings or thread it means to separate
your embroidery floss to that number so
i'm using two strands throughout this
project so i'm twisting it the opposite
way and i'm making a two-strand one and
this makes your embroidery floss go a
long way as well
and then tie a knot at the end of your
embroidery string this is just how i
choose to do my knots but there's lots
of different ways to do them
and then lastly i'm showing you tying
knots on the back of your project you
want to tie a knot hold your finger down
so it's at the base and then cut off the
tail and that is everything that i do to
set up my projects i'm going to show you
a little time lapse now of me finishing
up this pattern and the stitch that i'm
currently using will be listed somewhere
on the screen and now i'm going to
answer your questions just in the form
of tips the first one is just going to
be that i'm using a floor embroidery
stand you can buy these if you want
assistance in doing the two-handed
embroidery stitches but you can also
just have your hoop hang over the side
of a table for the two-handed stitches
for embroidering on black or dark fabric
you're going to want to use light when
tracing on your pattern and you also
will want to use a white charcoal pencil
on the fabric rather than just a regular
mechanical pencil
i definitely get lazy and do this one
myself but i recommend not jumping long
distances behind your hoop with your
thread to start a new stitch just
because if you're using really thin
fabric sometimes it will show through
if your thread ever gets twisted and
your stitches start to appear really
thin then just drop the needle and let
it hang freely until it unwinds and also
if your thread ever gets in a knot or
tangled using the needle is really
helpful to kind of poke through those
knots and undo them
if you need to take out a bunch of
stitches that you messed up on then just
cut off the knot at the back of the hoop
and then cut the back side of the
stitches and then you can use your
needle on the other side to pull them up
and out of your fabric
and lastly if you're ever purchasing a
pattern they usually come at a set size
i typically have mine set for five inch
hoops but if you save that file and just
pop it into a document then you can
resize it to whichever size hoop that
you're using
last part of this video i have finished
the project and now i'm going to show
you how i finish them off completely so
i'm taking it off of my floor stand
and then i'm going to grab my wooden
hoop again i'm using the five inch for
this one
take both of the hoops apart and your
fabric out of the plastic hoop
and then just flip your fabric over and
align it with the inside portion of that
wooden hoop
you can use the plastic one as a guide
to make sure that it's centered and
everything
and then you're just going to put the
outside portion over top trying to
center it as much as possible and you
can see the wrinkles have appeared again
which means that it's not pulled tight
all the way so i'm going to tighten it
just a little bit and then i'm going to
start pulling the fabric through the
back again
and really trying to get it centered and
exactly where i want it on this wooden
one
and there's lots of ways to finish off
the back of your hoop i personally use
hot glue so when i'm happy with the
position of my stitching i then go in
the back and i just put hot glue
directly in between the hoop and the
fabric and i fold it over throughout
this whole process i'm making sure to
pull the fabric very tight i don't want
to also drip any hot glue onto my
project so i'm getting it just on the
edge there and i'm being mindful that it
is hot glue and i'm making sure not to
burn myself
[Music]
the last step is to trim off the excess
fabric i usually use pinking shears for
this so it doesn't fray but these ones
work as well
and that is everything that i do during
my embroidery process let me know if you
have any questions down in the comments
but i tried to be as thorough as
possible throughout this video
[Music]
i hope you enjoyed that video if you did
give it a thumbs up and subscribe if you
haven't already like i mentioned my etsy
shop is going to be in the description
box i have several different patterns on
there as well as the beginner embroidery
pattern let me know down in the comments
if you have any embroidery videos that
you'd like to see for me or any patterns
that you would like me to make as always
i hope you all have a wonderful week and
i'll see you next time bye
[Music]
you